Guide to WNYU (Radio Station: New York, N.Y.) Records 1949- 1969 RG 39.5
New York University Libraries
WNYU (Radio Station: New York, N.Y.) Records
1949-1969
RG 39.5
1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
New York University Archives
WNYU
WNYU was formed in 1949 on the University Heights campus of New York University by a group of engineers. The records of WNYU Radio Station were transferred to the New York University Archives when the radio station was moved from Gould Memorial library at University Heights, to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square in June 1973. Materials include correspondence, minutes, reports, drawings, and promotional material.
Provenance
The records of WNYU Radio Station were transferred to the New York University Archives when the radio station was moved from Gould Memorial library at University Heights, to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square in June 1973. The records, 16 linear inches of material, cover the years 1949-1969 and deal with the activities of WNYU radio station and the efforts and persistence of WNYU's staff to build up an AM-FM radio station and maintain its broadcasting as one of the best educational radio stations in the New York metropolitan area. The collection is predominately composed of correspondence between WNYU's staff and other constituent parts of the University. Other correspondence relates to the broader media and metropolitan community.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers.
Historical Note
WNYU was formed in 1949 on the University Heights campus of New York University by a group of engineers. Initially, the station only broadcast to the University Heights' cafeteria. Well established by 1956, WNYU became a member of the Inter-Collegiate Broadcasting System (IBS). In 1955 the radio division of the Television, Motion Picture and Radio Department of the Communications Arts Group started a closed circuit station WCAG at the Washington Square Campus. In 1963 WNYU (Heights Station) and WCAG (Washington Square Station) merged into one closed circuit radio station through the use of a telephone cable. It was decided that WCAG would broadcast to both campuses during the day while WNYU would take over in the evenings. This continued until 1973 when NYU sold the Heights campus. At that time the equipment was brought to Loeb Student Center on Washington Square. During the period of 1965-1973 the station worked to acquire an FM frequency. In 1965 NYU made an agreement with the United Nations to use their channel, "206." NYU submitted their first application to the Federal Communication Commission (FCC) in 1965. After three years the FCC decided that channel "206" should be shared by NYU and Fairleigh Dickinson University of New Jersey. WNYU broadcast from 4 p.m. to 1 a.m. on weekdays.
Scope and Content Note
The records include correspondence of Joseph Steinberg, the station's manager during the 1960s with University offices; the Inter-Colligiate Broadcasting System; and Miller, Montgomery & Spanding concerning construction for WNYU facilities. Also correspondence of Larry J. Hollander, the faculty advisor to the WYNU staff, with Steinberg; correspondence of the staff with fellow radio stations including the Columbia University station, concerning such topics as the election of 1964, Ray Nelson, and a Senator Claiborne Pell interview about youth legislation; letters from The New York Times to Arnold Rosner, Director of Classical Music at NYU; letters from the Police Department of New York City; and letters from United Press International. Also included are minutes of meetings of the WNYU Board of Directors, budget reports and operating expense estimates of WNYU members, log forms, schedules, applications, architectural drawings, certificates from Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company, advertising brochures, programs, newsletters, and printed promotional material.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically; series II is arranged alphabetically by subject; and series III is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
This collection has been organized into three series:
I. Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda
II. Drawings
III. Publications
Access Points
Subject Names:
Steinberg, Joseph; Hollander, Larry J.; Nelson, Ray.; Pell, Claiborne, 1918-; Rosner, Arnold
Subject Topics:
Radio--Equipment and supplies.; Radio broadcasting--Archival resources.; Radio broadcasting--History.; Radio broadcastingâManagement.; Radio broadcasting--Rules and regulations.; Radio in education.
Organizations:
Inter-Collegiate Broadcasting System (U.S.); Miller, Montgomery & Spanding.; Columbia University--Radio broadcasting.; New York University--Radio broadcasting.; New York Times Company.; United Press International.; Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company.; Fairleigh Dickinson University (New Jersey)--Radio broadcasting.; United Nations.; New York (N.Y.). Police Dept.; New York University. Communications Arts Group.; WNYU (Radio station: New York, N.Y.); WCAG (Radio station: New York, N.Y.)
Document Types:
Architectural drawings.; Advertisements.; Minutes.; Petitions.; Applications.; Newsletters.
Container List
- Series I: Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda: 1949-1969.
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 29, 1949 -April 8, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 17, 1955 -Dec. 27, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, 1955-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 28, 1956 -May 7, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Dec. 9, 1957 -Sept. 23, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 5, 1958 -Mar. 18, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 29, 1960 -Nov. 15, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 20, 1960 -Feb. 27, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 8, 1962 -Nov. 12, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Mar. 1, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Mar. 1, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 3, 1963 -May 14, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 7, 1963 -Dec. 6, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Aug. 10, 1964-May 25, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 11, 1964 -May 12, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 5, 1964 -Mar. 11, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Dec. 14, 1964 -Apr. 18, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 21, 1964 -Jun. 15, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 12, 1965 -Dec. 18, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 29, 1965 -Sept. 22, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Aug. 31, 1965 -May 16, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Oct. 14, 1965 -Oct. 19, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 18, 1965 -Apr. 19, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Radio Station WFDU, 1965 -1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Convention, 1965 -1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 17, 1966-Aug. 15, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Feb. 21, 1966 -Oct. 31, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Nov. 22, 1966 -Apr. 18, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 17, 1967 -Dec. 4, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Apr. 6, 1967 -Jun. 6, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jun. 17, 1968 -Dec. 20, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, minutes, legal documents, memoranda, Jan. 6, 1969 -Feb. 6, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - WNYU log forms, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series II: Drawings
  - Drawings of WNYU radio station, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Drawings of WNYU radio station, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series III: Publications
  - Newspapers, Feb. 1967 -May 1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers, Jan. 1957 -Oct. 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Printed material, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
Related Material at the New York University Archives
Sidney Borowitz Papers, Box 58, Folder 17 (July 1972 - August 1975)